[Music]
does this hurt your eyes this is too
bright for you that true okay I'm going
to bring it down a little bit is that
okay
yeah I E for school lunch is chips a a
hamburger the chickens are always cold
and they're like dry and they're hard
and it's hard for people to eat it I see
like a lot of grease on it cuz there's
lots of grease on the top and after they
finish it there's so much grease inside
of it the pizza is really good but it's
actually not healthy for
you we have a real crisis in our country
I know a lot lot of people call it the
Obesity
crisis but we call it a crisis of poor
health obesity just happens to be the
most visible sign 50% of children
between the ages of 2 and 15 have fatty
streaks in their arteries and this is
literally the beginning stages of heart
disease and it's totally preventable
this affects children across every
single demographic it affects the rich
it affects the poor it affects children
of all Races nobody is safe from the
dangers of the child obesity epidemic in
most schools in America today there is
no healthy choice they get foods from
the federal government and in many cases
they're not the healthiest things
they're not getting huge truckloads of
vegetables and fruits ready to turn into
healthy meals they get a lot of surplus
cheese Surplus meats and when you see
what's in the cafeteria now you can't
blame the lunch workers they don't have
anything but an alto sham to like you
know heat food up to a safe temperature
and it's barely food at that we have no
budgets and no concern about what we're
pumping into our kids and then we wonder
why they don't like food we dumbed down
their palets I look at schools as
setting an example for the kinds of
foods that kids ought to be eating and
if they're eating junk food in schools
then the schools are telling them that
that's okay it's appropriate it's what
happens in schools that's not right
they're probably in that environment 8
hours so all of a sudden 20 minutes was
devoted to a decent meal the parents
don't want to change a lot of this and
the children can't change it I'm afraid
I it gets to be survival of the fittest
in many ways you know some of these
people will be tossed aside literally
and figuratively by the
system kids are getting this idea
ingrained in them that real nutrition
doesn't count and it doesn't really
matter because if it really mattered the
school nutrition program would provide
them with really high quality food every
day
so much has changed from when I was a
kid when I was a kid we still had
vocational training as part of your
public school program everybody took a
certain amount of Home e you took shop
you could learn these basic sets of
skills where you could get a job if you
graduated from high school and you'd
have all these basic skills you could
fix your car you could fix yourself
dinner you were a whole human being and
little by little I think we became so
worried about just test scores just test
scores and funding became an issue
making it smaller not bigger and we
started taking from our own kids I don't
know where that happened and then the
lunchrooms got attacked and the lunch
ladies and the lunch men that used to
prepare Foods were given less and less
equipment and less and less money again
we took from our own children good
nutritious food breakfast programs
disappeared intramural activities
disappeared vocational training
disappeared we really dumbed down our
entire society and not just when it
comes to the food to make them book
smart our children sacrificed in every
way imaginable literally gives me chills
like a horror movie horror movie to
[Applause]
[Music]
me
I I think that if there were healthy
meals provided to them at breakfast and
at lunch um it would just improve their
whole life because they would eat better
they would feel better they would study
you know more effectively they would you
know be able to be at gym and have
sustained a sustained energy level
and try to draw it on your um on your
work not having good food I think has a
direct impact on a child's ability to
learn um and focus in the classroom uh
you know can stand up sitting in that
chair
WR we can tell when our kids are hungry
we know when they're distracted we know
when they're irritable and especially if
they really haven't eaten at home or
they didn't eat the night before at home
you know their first meal might be here
and so if that meal is
you know something that is not providing
them with any nutrition whatsoever then
what value is
[Music]
it
I
[Music]
am a lot of our kids eat breakfast here
and lunch and have an afternoon snack
and so we've done a few things that we
think helped that just by providing
fruit or healthy snacks at times when we
don't normally provide them or having
you know apples and fresh grapes at you
know at events instead of cookies so
we've done you know we've I think tried
to impact it in small ways but not ways
that sort of help my conscience now it's
time to leave for lunch so see you later
I hate chicken
PS know they stink like poop how about
lunch I eat lunch and it tastes good but
sometimes I think in as a school
principal it's one of those things that
um I feel like my conscience is sort of
working against me because when I go
down there and we're serving it I know
that I don't want to eat it and that I
don't think it's healthy but yet I'm
serving it to 600 kids um and that's a
conflict for me almost every day
often times in the lunch line they'll
either be complaining I don't want that
or we usually have to like finagle with
the kids if you want salad if you want
panut bread jelly if you want the hot
lunch and we have to try to like bargain
with them about what they want to eat um
and that usually causes you know some
sort of a fight um with students and um
them not being um sorry being really
distracted um and them not being like a
happy person during lunch and you know
we always want lunch to be a time that
the kids are enjoying each other and
enjoying their friends but if they're
not you know eating the food then
they're sitting there either upset or
hungry for the rest of the day this is
what I was talking
about we've had times when we have had
food served that's either Frozen or
molded or you know just or a whole pile
of apples that are not fresh you know or
you bite into an apple and it's like a
soggy mush well you wouldn't eat that
and you would throw it away at home why
is it not being thrown away at school um
um and I know that I love our kitchen
stuffff I think they work very hard to
help us they work very hard to you know
do what they can with what they have but
what they're being provided with is not
enough to provide a healthy meal for our
kids all of us the teachers and everyone
of feeling like the parents are trusting
us with their kids and therefore
assuming that we're not giving them
anything that we wouldn't eat but we the
adults don't actually eat get to eat
down there so you don't even have that
rub because we don't eat the food we
have you know we go out out to get food
um but yep I think I don't think no I
don't think parents really understand
what they're being served and no I don't
think um that I do think that if they
knew what the food looked like and the
sort of the caliber and the quality of
the food and the lack you know sort of
the unhealthy nature of the food I think
they would be
upset healthy what does that mean
but then what should you be e what does
it take what are just some of the things
you think we've been talking about
health for a while now and they teach us
about what we're supposed to be eating
and how what a healthy diet looks like
and it kind of contradicts itself when
they say we need to be eating right it
actually didn't even make sense because
I was learning all about my health in
health class and in the cafeteria they
serve you like cookies and stuff cookies
an ice
cream school lunch is um sometimes it's
okay but other times I just don't know
what I'm
eating we'll be in school for like till
4:00 and then when we do have lunch it's
at um 1:00 so people be
hungry so I'm getting online got my food
and it was on this tortilla bed and I
didn't know what it was so that's the
worst kind of food when you don't know
know what it is and it doesn't even look
good I couldn't eat it my conscience
wouldn't let me they'll drop the tray in
the garbage and just drink the milk and
then they'll go to the rest of day being
hungry and then when I walk outside of
school I can't really blame them for
going to pizzerias and the fast food
restaurants but at the same time that's
what I'm teaching them not to go to so
it's incredibly frustrating to see you
know this trend that we're kind of
creating in our own school if you have
to pick up a tray in our school you
can't just say I'm not eating so I would
like to tell them I want you one day to
eat the school lunch and see how we
feel in the 1930s farmers in the United
States faced a terrible depression in
agriculture cult that was actually more
profound than the industrial depression
because it had been going on for almost
a decade when what we think of as the
Great Depression began farmers were left
with very heavy Mortgage Debt many of
them had mortgaged their farms in order
to expand Farm production during the war
in order to try to pay it off they tried
to produce more and the more they
produced the more surpluses they had and
the more the price
declined they were in a terrible
downward
spiral when the Roosevelt administration
came into power in March of 1933 one of
their highest priorities was to get some
relief to Farmers and they couldn't
really do that as long as the surpluses
were holding prices down the
administration passed the agricultural
adjustment act um which gave the federal
government new tools for were managing
Farm
surpluses in Chicago the hog Farmers had
lots and lots and lots of baby pigs and
because there was some actual shortage
in the corn Supply it was expensive to
feed those pigs uh and so the secretary
of agriculture agreed to buy 6 million
baby pigs and slaughter them before they
grew up to be big Hogs they were ground
up for something that's called tankage
which is a kind of liquefied pig and in
Chicago they chose an Old Quarry dumped
a lot of the tankage into the Quarry and
the weather turned hot there was a
terrible smell and everything to call
attention to the fact that the
government was sponsoring the
destruction of of good
food there was a major public outcry uh
Roosevelt was very Savvy about public
relations and he ordered a
high-profile cooperation between the
agriculture Department and the federal
emergency relief Administration to
create a program to procure the farmer
surpluses and process and distribute
them for the
[Music]
unemployed out of that cooperation grew
School food and that actually triggered
our whole array of federal domestic food
assistance
[Music]
programs the USDA in the 1930s would
take that Surplus and ship it off to
schools for free the program was
mandated to serve whole milk and butter
and cream and custard because a
nutritionist believed that poor children
were not getting enough calories
[Music]
the Department of Agriculture was
established to look after the nation's
lands and um farming and and to help the
nation's Farmers now it does have an
interest in keeping food prices
affordable but it also has an interest
in supporting the Food Industries USDA
is an agency that is inherently
conflicted and that's not just when it
comes to school launch they have they
have dual roles they are a they have a
food safety component and an oversight
and a regulatory function with respect
to the food industry and they also have
by law a promotional and marketing
responsibility to support us Agriculture
and to support the food industry and to
help promote and grow the food industry
and those those missions certainly I
think come into conflict there the
question of whether they're putting the
interests of Industry ahead of the
interests of students is much more
difficult to pinned down um again they
have both of these roles by law by
Statute and we never found any Smoking
Gun where you know there was a memo that
said we know this food isn't good for
kids but we're going to buy it anyway
because we want to support the
industry we found that um both the
quality standards and the safety
standards for a lot of the meat that's
purchased for school lunches were far
less than what you see in a lot of the
commercial side and one of the things
that we're surprised by was a particular
kind of chicken think it's commonly
referred to a spent hen meat and this is
meat from egg laying birds that have
been retired that are no longer
producing eggs and nobody really uses
them much on the commercial Market even
Kentucky Fried Chicken to McDonald's
declines to buy this stuff and it is in
some cases commonly sold to the pet food
industry they use it for pet food and
the school lunch program bought a lot of
it they bought about 77 million pounds
between 2001 and
2009 the school lunch program tried
using it in patties using it in salads
and that kind of thing and um eventually
backed off the practice although there's
still I believe some being
purchased
[Applause]
schools can piece together meals in lots
of different ways but whatever they do
it needs to come with the milk so the
dairy industry is really benefiting from
the school lunch program but at the same
time milk is a healthy food if it's low
in fat whole milk 2% milk even though
provides calcium it's not really worth
it because the saturated fat that comes
along with it isn't isn't worth the
calcium because it clogs arteries and
contributes to heart disease dairy
products that have so many uses that
athletes depend on in building strong
healthy bodies milk doesn't just play a
role
in formation of bone there are other
health benefits because of the unique
nutrient package that dairy foods have
that we need to be eating those three
servings every day whether we choose to
use lowfat non-fat lactose-free whatever
our choice may be thinking more about
the the food lunch program and the fact
that it's pushing things on kids that
are not not even healthy for them so if
we know that you know black and Latino
kids shouldn't drink milk or that a lot
of them a lot of us are lactose
intolerant why are we forcing them to
have milk that has you know does not
take care of that or why aren't there
other options for them I mean this is an
example of dairy industry lobbying at
work very successfully convincing the
Department of Agriculture that if you
don't drink milk you don't get calcium
and that milk is an essential nutrient
it's not there are many cultures in the
world where kids don't drink milk and
somehow they manag to
survive
there are alternatives and if for health
reasons or religious reasons or just
because you don't like the taste kids
should have alternative options to milk
and and I think it's very reasonable to
provide soy milk or water other
beverages for kids to choose and you
shouldn't need a doctor's note in order
to get that
alternative every single food tra
Association is concerned that nothing be
done to advise eating less of their
products that's just good business sense
and since food corporations fund
election campaigns they have a great
deal of
say I worked for the government for two
years from 1986 to 1988 and I was the
editor of of a big fat report called the
surgeon general's report on nutrition
and health which was the first Federal
report linking diet to chronic disease
vention and the it was the report was
heavily lobbied although I was not the
recipient of the lobbying efforts the
person who ran our office was but on the
first day that I was there and I tell
the story in my book food Politics on
the first day that I arrived in the
office I was told that the report would
never say eat less meat in fact you
probably wouldn't say eat less of
anything because whatever industry it
was that that advice affected
would go to Congress and complain and
the report would never come out and so
the report's recommendations were
phrased largely in euphemisms and the
big recommendation of the report was eat
less fat it didn't say eat less
meat big corporations in the food Lobby
matter a great deal the reimbursement
comes from the US Department of
Agriculture uh I think that that says a
lot and um those companies do matter um
and that's just I think the way the
political structure in America with food
is set up and there's it's some perhaps
some change in discussion around that I
think it's long
[Music]
overdo
school lunch is uh it's a more difficult
Endeavor than I think most people
realize a lot goes into it uh what most
people see is on the front end like I
suppose in any organization and the most
important part are the meals being
served to the children you have the
kitchen staff Local Kitchen facilities
the preparation of the food beyond that
is the ordering of the food uh the
supply chain and the distribution beyond
that the centralized staff that deals
with things like accountability Health
control inspections for instance then
beyond that you have the management and
it's all sort of held together with the
glue of reimbursement from the United
States Department of Agriculture the
national school lunch and breakfast
program serves 7 billion meals a year in
the United States this is not a small
operation it's in 99,000 schools by the
time you take out the labor and
administrative costs and increasingly
the bill for electricity in the
cafeteria gas some schools even charge
the school food operation for check
writing you do have typically a dollar
or less to spend on food it's not very
much
money five components for 90s we're
talking
[Music]
about for our children who are our
future and so we really need to increase
the amount of money that we put into
school meals we can talk about the
reasons why it is the way it is but the
bottom line is we need to change it and
you know when we look at the school meal
the school lunch um there is about 90
cents that's being spent on the food
components 20 cents of which come from
the commodity Foods those are the foods
supplied essentially for free to the
schools complements of our federal tax
dollars and the top three foods in the
commodity programs are are beef like
ground beef chicken and and cheese the
ground beef ends up as hamburgers the
cheese ends up as deep fried mozzarella
sticks or pizza and the chicken ends up
as chicken nuggets pretty much straight
across the board you know that's what's
served over and over again in schools
and so we need to we need to look at
this we spend more than $5 a meal on
meals at senior centers in in New York
City um there's a soup kitchen in lower
Manhattan that
is investing an average of $7 a meal
it's really almost too much to put your
head around and it's why I really don't
understand why we have to have a
conversation asking for a buck for for
our kids for each child you know or
asking for a summer food program like
why are we even debating this why is
this even a conversation and that's
where you can get hung up again and you
get so frustrated and worked up you get
nothing done Financial incentives that
Washington will set will have a per
profound impact on school lunches
Nationwide in order to maximize our
budgets we need to rely on the donated
Commodities that are offered to us by
the USDA and we've been working with the
USDA to improve those Commodities and
they have for example their vegetables
are low sodium now they've reduced the
fat in a lot of their products and
they're also trying to make it happen
but because we're under this you know
large sort of um system of Commodities
and Food Service all under one it makes
it very challenging to make that happen
for 90 cents to a dollar for the entire
meal now we're talking about a program
that costs the government 12 billion a
year um and kids also buy food in
schools with their own money so you're
talking about something that's big bucks
and there's a lot of money at stake and
every food company wants to be in on the
action the orders tend to be quite large
when USDA is buying ground beef for
schools it it's often buying it in tens
of thousands or hundreds of thousands of
pounds at a
time by and large the the the ground
beef and the poultry that are being
purchased for school lunches are being
purchased from large scale suppliers you
don't see a lot of small mom and pop
Farms that are supplying USDA with
ground beef for the lunch program you
have to be what they call a qualified
supplier which means that you have to
demonstrate to USDA that you can meet
certain food safety requirements that
you have processes in place to minimize
the chances that meat is going to become
contaminated um and that you can meet
their testing requirements for that beef
and for that chicken and so forth and in
fact the State Department of Health said
today they believe that this recall will
spread they've been trying to track down
which Distributors actually took the
beef in question and then sold it on
down the food chain to the consumer you
know some of the things I've read it's
unbelievable did you know that if
there's a recall for or meat for example
that goes all around the country no one
bothers to tell the schools there are
5,000 kids in Franklin schools and on
any given day most if not all may eat
from the cafeteria but it's unclear if
any of the recalled meat ever reach
their plate and so the schools will cook
it and and and feed it to the children
the children who are the most vulnerable
to food born diseases are the least
protected that that the systems that
were in place when there is a problem
with food that's been purchased by
schools is very fractured and there
there's no there's no consistent or
particularly effective mechanism for
getting the word out to other schools
that may have bought the same products
school districts in three dozen states
across the country are scrambling to get
rid of the recalled meat the recall
includes 143 million pounds of beef it
comes after Humane Society videotaped
disturbing images from a California meat
processing plan the images show sick
cows being kicked dragged and shoved
into the slaughter housee much of the
meat has already been eaten here's what
other other school districts have done
about the recalled beef Guilford County
schools use some of it but pulled the
remaining beef Randolph County says it
received the meat last year and used all
of it unfortunately we don't have a way
to track if the meat was served or not
there's no way for us to know because
once it's served the boxes are broken
down and thrown out and we don't have a
track of the skew numbers that came
through so sometimes the suppliers may
be aware that their food has gone to
schools but they may not even be because
they're selling their food to
Distributors and the Distributors are
then selling their food sometimes to
buyers for schools or to Food Service
contractors that have been hired by
schools to run their cafeterias and what
we found is that it's very it's it's
it's very difficult to ensure that that
message gets all the way down to the
schools or even to know which schools
got it schools typically have no idea
where most of the food that they're
serving children comes
from it's more complicated than just
saying why is the school lunch program
providing these Foods Foods It's a
larger question about what does the food
industry in the US look like these
days we have a food system in this
country that produces twice as many
calories as the country needs on average
food companies have to sell that and
they not only have to sell food in this
enormously competitive environment but
they must meet demands of Wall Street to
not only make a profit but grow their
profits every 90 days this puts food
corporations in an especially difficult
situation because they're trying to sell
food in an environment which is twice as
much food as anybody needs and grow at
the same time so the result of that is
that they have looked for ways to Market
Foods well beyond the grocery
store food is everywhere and they know
that in order to get people people to
buy more food than they need or want
they must make food readily accessible
instantly available extremely convenient
and cheap and the result of that is
obesity not because food companies are
sitting around a corporate boardroom
saying how do we make Americans fat
that's not what they're trying to do
they're sitting around corporate
boardrooms saying how do we get people
to buy more products in an environment
in which there's already tons of food
available that nobody wants needs when I
was a kid you couldn't eat lunch in a
gas station when you went to the drug
store you didn't have to walk through
three aisles of junk food to get to the
prescription
department now junk food is
everywhere it's not like you find
baskets of apples and bananas at the
checkout stand no that's where the junk
food is that's where the candy and the
chocolate bars
are the advertising ing has increased
drastically in this country over the
last couple of decades I like the
northern European model where they don't
allow advertising to children under a
certain age I think that's fair and
that's right that they shouldn't be
advertising food that is detrimental to
their health to young kids the purpose
of marketing to Children is threefold
one is brand loyalty um you get a child
convinced that a particular brand is
better that child you hope will choose
that brand throughout life the second is
called the pester factor and it's just
what it sounds like you want kids not
only to pester their parents but also to
do it in an intelligent way you should
buy this product because it's got fiber
in it for example and then the third is
the one that I think is the most
important and that is you want kids to
think that they're supposed to be eating
kids food they're supposed to be eating
food made just for them in funny shapes
and color
packages unidentified food objects
whatever you don't want kids thinking
that they're supposed to eat the same
old boring adult foods that their
parents are hopefully eating and that is
so undermining of Parental Authority
around food issues that I think it's
reason enough to be really concerned
about this kind of thing the pressure
really is on every time you turn on the
television set half the commercials are
for snack foods and junk foods and the
other half of the commercials are for
medications to undo all the effects of
snack foods that they're
[Music]
promoting kids grow up in this junk food
culture that is America today and they
expect to be fed this
junk these are youngsters who are
subjected to 10 to 12 billion dollar a
year of food advertising and the
advertising is not for fresh fruits and
vegetables
that's weird how did your gushers get in
my hand gushers fruit flavored snacks
it's fast food and highly processed
packaged foods and that's what kids are
that's what kids think they
[Music]
[Applause]
want yogurt slurp till it's FL there's
this excitement around the junk food so
even though my kid loves dates and
raisins As a
treat he now wants cupcakes and Candy
because there's this party atmosphere
around those Foods there's never a party
when the kids get
[Music]
broccoli fast food is an American
concept we created that industry it came
along with our car our culture it came
about in this time of
prosperity look we're all working so
hard we're happy Americans we deserve
this kind of food and look you get a toy
with it too so it's this whole emotional
package in that box it's not just the
food it's this image of happy healthy
American families doing something
together when in reality that food is
slowly killing
[Music]
US President Reagan today opened his
second White House news conference with
some bad news for the bureaucracy fewer
government workers and a slashed federal
payroll millions of Americans today have
had to tighten their belts because of
the economic conditions and it's time to
put Washington on a diet
too in the the early 1980s there was a
major cut back in the federal subsidy
for for school foods and this put School
food operators the the food service
departments in a tremendous financial
crunch so the upshot was that school
food service was urged to operate like a
business and break even and they began
to try and lure those pay customers back
into the program by offering more and
more of kids favorite
foods we've had officials in the
department of UC education in the office
of school food tell us that they have to
keep their numbers up for the lunches
that they're in the business of serving
lunch and they want to give the children
what they want I eat like three like two
slices of pizza meal serve macaroni with
bread I usually eat like grilled cheese
like I won't eat all of this but I'll
eat the chips Jell-O sometimes like on
the side it was some meat type of meat
it was like pinkish and chicken chicken
nugget at ice cream pizza turkey
sandwiches with a lot of turkey and Mayo
on it butter and some mayonnaise and
some mustard so it's nasty it's just
like a milk with like cookies and that's
it and bagels with cream cheese or
butter I
ate hm what else I eat really the
flavored milk and the hamburgers and the
chicken nuggets and the pizza I believe
they're all in the menu because those
those are the foods that kids like so
those Foods continue to stay even though
everyone knows they're not healthy it's
fast
food when people are not starving to
death it's
different we're overfed and
undernourished in this country if people
were starving in the streets that would
be a different level of
anxiety but because it's a slow death
people don't take notice as much they're
not as worried about it they're not as
as apt to make big
changes I don't believe if anyone walked
into a school cafeteria and saw the
environment that's in our schools that
they would be proud of it
whatsoever and I think there's a lot of
passivity on the part of policy makers
and
parents they believe that this is the
best that we can do and it's good enough
and we need to understand that no we can
we can change this um and we can
certainly improve it that we need to do
that back in 1946 when the generals came
forward and said you know we've got a
population out there that can't serve in
the military because they're under nurse
well we're a victim of our own success
it's not a question of being under nurse
we're over nursed and we're over nursed
with empty
calories if we don't do something we
need to accept the fact that we will not
be the leaders of the world we will not
be the folks that are bringing the
inventions to the table the
breakthroughs in technology and offer
folks uh a better way of life
in the United States nearly 2third of
the population is
overweight almost one in three Americans
is obese and no one wants to
be Americans want to be thinner and yet
old and young Americans are getting
fatter and fatter and fatter we all
think it's our own fault it is not that
simple I think it's embarrassing for the
United States that we don't feed our
kids better that we don't educate our
kids is better and that we have so many
children living in poverty that's
embarrassing there are 17 million
American children that could literally
go hungry every day that they're not in
school cuz the only access they get to
food at all is school food then you have
the next door neighbor to the hungry a
third of our kids are overweight or
obese we have kids as young as nine
taking cholesterol
medicines trying to clean out their
arteries
we did that to
them as we've seen the decline of the
middle class in this country you just
see these guilt-ridden parents that are
emotionally
exhausted they don't have enough money
to pay all the bills and buy a decent
week's groceries naively and blissfully
they want to imagine that their kids are
getting this big hug when they go to
school that they're getting the best
education and the best food and the best
exercise and that they're having a much
better existence while they're out
earning a couple of
bucks it's
absolutely awful I really can't think
about it too much it really it's awful
and it's a really ironic thing for me
because I don't think I'd have a job
unless there was a couple of generations
of people that didn't know how to
[Music]
cook the school lunch program was
devised years ago when the concern was
children aren't getting enough to eat
maybe that lunch is the biggest meal of
the day so they made sure that the law
said it has to have a certain number of
calories in order to to pass well
nowadays we know that the problem is the
opposite kids need a little bit fewer
calories so we need some flexibility
there or otherwise we're never going to
conquer the Obesity
epidemic
we are teaching our kids to celebrate
almost any emotion with food something
good happens you give them Pizza
something bad happens you give them
pizza and then for lunch you give them
pizza so we're sending such mixed
messages and then we tell them to eat
healthy and make a healthy choice it's
no wonder our kids are so confused
thought there were supposed to be on
diets I think they're
cheating
you would think that if a parent had a
choice of what to bring in to celebrate
either good grades or a birthday you'd
think they'd bring something healthy but
they don't they bring very unhealthy
Foods it's almost always ice cream
cupcakes huge cupcakes that they give to
these little kids and the kids eat them
because they're put in front of them
it's it's unfortunate but parents they
want to be the good guy I found you know
my son broke his arm last year and and
we were in the hospital and I kept
saying honey when this is over I'm
taking you to friendlies we're going to
get hot fudge Sundays honey we're going
to get hot fudge Sundays and I thought
about it afterwards that was my instinct
to tell him this is bad but we're going
to celebrate it with something really
unhealthy I was actually disappointed in
myself for having that reaction but it's
so ingrained in our society my heart
sinks every time I see an obese child
because I know they're being robbed of
some of the Vitality of life that they
could be experiencing at that time and
you know when you go through certain
periods of your life you can't get them
back if you miss you know your
adolescence it's gone I think the most
basic cause of the child obesity uh
epidemic is what I call portion
Distortion our kids are just eating way
too much food they're eating so many
more calories than they need and studies
show that by the age of five if you put
a larger portion of food in front of a
child they're going to eat more about
25% more calories not only do they take
more spoonfuls of food but they actually
unconsciously put more on each spoonful
when they served a larger portion I was
at a tennis match couple years ago and
um glattus Knight was singing the
National Anthem and she had a set of you
know high school girls from a choir you
know from a New York City school behind
her and I just looked at the bleach
where those girls were standing and I
said my goodness every one of them has a
weight issue and they're 16 17 years old
my question is if we're supposed to be
educating kids in school why isn't their
education in the cafeteria too because
obviously people are eating what they
think they should be eating they don't
know what to eat anymore so our
overweight kids are discriminated
against not only socially by their peers
but by their teachers by other school
administrators many adults don't realize
that they're doing it but you just
naturally prefer dealing with a normal
weight person the scientific studies
show that over and over again so you
know we think that if we talk to our
overweight children about weight we're
going to give them a poor self-esteem
that's not the case these overweight
kids have poor self-esteem already by
talking about the issue and giving them
the tools to make healthy changes you
can actually increase the child's
self-esteem dramatically ignoring it is
not the answer I've suffered from my own
addictions as a result of food you know
I used to have to have ice cream in my
house all the time and I couldn't go
home if the ice cream wasn't there or if
I came home and there wasn't enough ice
cream there I had to leave I had to go
get my hog and dos or I wasn't going to
be comfortable at home and every time I
had a meal regardless of whether I was
dieing or trying to eat the right things
I I my body craved that sugar before it
would let me alone and when I finally
got free of the whole thing and I
thought about my behavior I said Robin
if this was any other
substance what would you call your
behavior and I said to myself wow if it
was heroin if it was cigarettes you
would call me an
addict having become vegan and and
fasting I've had the opportunity to be
away from food to watch how many prompts
we get for food all day long to listen
to the conversations people have about
food they're they're at breakfast
talking about what they're going to have
for lunch and at lunch they're talking
about what they're going to have for
dinner they don't even realize they're
eating when they have a snack but we're
eating all day long the body's digestion
is working all day long and we wonder
why we're so tired
we have to get back to eating healthy
and if it takes everybody getting sick
and an epidemic of diabetes and heart
disease and early death maybe that's
what's going to wake people
up you know I really think that a lot of
people are in the position where they've
been kind of they've they've done well
in life they just haven't done good
yet I went to a Jesuit High School here
in San Jose and the Jesuits are very
good at pulling you back in once you've
been successful and uh they pulled me
back in to do a middle school here in
San Jose about 10 years ago and I think
it doesn't take long before you do a
school like that before you realize it's
very transformative for the neighborhood
and it's just a great Mission and I was
looking for a better Mission uh I had
come out of tech Tech's great you make a
lot of people a lot of money but uh you
know at the end of the day is the world
really a lot better place because of
what you do for for me uh it's
low-income kids and the needs of
low-income kids that are the greatest
Injustice that we have so from a Justice
standpoint the fact that you're born
here versus paloalto should make any
difference and that's really what rocket
ship's about is is getting rid of that
problem and so that's just a passion of
mine is is making sure that wherever
you're born you have the same
opportunity to be successful in life
when we uh opened rocket ship we kind of
sat down and thought about food that
many school districts serve to their
kids you want to go to a place in a
cafeteria where the food that's being
served is food you'd like to eat
yourself and so we partnered with an
organization called Revolution foods
which does healthy food they're kind of
the in our opinion the the Whole Foods
of school food
service and their mission is to provide
very healthy food organic food to
schools at the federal reimburse rate
for free and reduced meals students 5
years we're serving 50,000 meals a day
Nationwide um yes there's problems
there's challenges there's things that
we need to figure out um but you got to
get out there and do it you've got to
get out there and be part of the
solution when we started Revolution
Foods our goal was to bridge an access
Gap in this country it was to make
healthy fresh delicious food available
to students in low-income communities
one of the things we found when we
started this company company is there
wasn't um the supply chain didn't
support healthy foods Nationwide so you
know we went to DC and we're like how do
we get a clean breed product for
instance so red Foods is I think not
only you know providing healthy meals in
schools but it's completely like
impacting the supply chain Nationwide in
terms of what's available we thought it
was important to show kids what what
healthy food looks like every
[Music]
day
you need to have a healthy meal platform
and you need to be nourishing kids from
the inside and outside I think every
time we put pressure on the system to
change you know we're catalyzing a much
bigger change across the
country what we're doing in New York
City with the school food project and
getting some of our yo meals
incorporated into the New York City
School food
diet is very much like what the First
Lady Michelle Obama uh and Sam the White
House Chef it's very much like what
they're doing with the chefs move on
Schools they're pairing up the
Nationwide registry of the greatest
chefs in our country we're calling on
them to do community service in the
public schools not to go in and change
everything but to go in and support and
help noodle it we're going to war
against obesity and War to bring healthy
food to kids and let's get all the great
minds and gather them together
nutritionist chefs uh people who put out
High volumes of food let's bring
everybody together and figure out a way
to get it to the kids one is cinnamon
and one is curry powder how about the
green snap peas and they want to try
those last night here at the restaurant
we opened with 120 covers we ended up
doing 180 I needed to still produce a
high quality food you know to the
customer so I wasn't going to just all a
sudden cook everything ahead of time and
just slam it onto a plate I think you
know I wanted to give the customers a
high quality experience so and I think
with the children they should get that
also I would like to introduce you to
Chef Billy dhy from New York City office
of school
food the New York Coalition for healthy
school food is a Statewide nonprofit and
it's the only Statewide nonprofit in the
country that focuses solely on school
food I completely 100% believe that
these type of programs can work in this
city in any city in the United States
and around the world there's a huge
network of chefs that have been working
um and you know everything is always
Grassroots so it really starts from the
bottom you're talking about people that
are donating their time volunteering um
donating the ingredients working to
bring people together through food and
that's a great thing and and all of us
uh all of us as chefs uh you know it's
our responsibility to help put the right
tools and the right food in the hands of
all these folks that want to be involved
and want to eat healthier and be and
just understand their food and know
where it comes from by educating the
students both through our Wellness
wakeup program and our family dinner
nights where we invite the whole family
in for dinner we have Hands-On learning
activities a cooking
demo
wow then everybody gets to eat a nice
dinner and then we have prizes and and
it's really been a great thing where
where the families learn together about
healthy school
[Music]
food I am so honored to be with you all
today so you could explore your inner
chefs minute
minute now you're right I have two
people to introduce to you today two
High School chefs chefs that are very
inspiring for me and I want you to
introduce you to christe hello and
Lazarus hi and they are let's give them
a big hand a big round of
applause what we're going to make for
you today is something called chickpea
of the sea chickpea of the
sea oh you're going to love it these
kids deserve a fighting chance and and
as a parent of young kids you know I
want to do everything for my children I
know every parent in America feels the
very same way and so we have to do
better by
them I like the
carrots
the salad I definitely like the beans
and rice and the salad do these beans
are the best my daughter was very glad
that she ate it and and I was seeing
that she enjoyed it and for myself I'm
learning how to cook different ways like
all the family get to enjoy theel open
their up and like be excited to eat like
fruits and vegetables they like to enjoy
their S I like to be happy this will be
a fun experience for the kids and they
can experience it with their families
and it's giving the kids the tools and
the knowledge about you know what's
nutritious where do we get the food from
and why is it better for our bodies this
is going to be a long battle because a
lot of kids don't understand the
relationship between Agriculture and the
food they eat and you know once the kids
learn the parents learn too and so it's
a great way to have that
conversation how is
[Applause]
it the biggest thing that we need to do
is get the kids involved and you know
get get them not so afraid in throwing
their hands into the dirt um we're not
too keen on shovels and brakes and stuff
so a lot of it's done with the hands you
want to kind of feel where the food is
coming
from look come here the idea of this
program is to teach kids how to plant
things show them where food comes from
show them different items that are grown
there's fresh mint there's broccoli
there's kale there's collards
cauliflower chives different flowers
tomatoes melons strawberries um and it's
just to expose them to the items that
are out there and then once the things
are done growing they're going to take
the items home with them expose them to
their family and show them fresh organic
produce that they have grown themselves
and this year we came out and uh with
the water that we've beting at the
beginning of the year it just kind of
took over the entire bed and um now we
have an entire Bed full of mint so um
you know we need to start becoming more
creative with mint recipes downstairs
when we're using certain items uh we try
to do as fresh as possible possible so
we'll call the farmer and say we need
this item now for beef or chicken or
turkey or whatever the item may be and
um get it in as we need it so the items
that you see in here are items that are
usually left over from you know the weak
production and uh we kind of circulate
them back in as we need them so things
like pizza and stuff like that is manade
specifically for us uh this pizza is
actually fortified with 14 vitamins and
minerals and the person who produced The
Forest name is Santi is a really great
individual um believes in fortifying uh
things sauces and uh DS and Breads and
stuff with um certain vitamins and
minerals that the kids wouldn't get on a
regular day basis so he presented this
item to us and it worked out really
well we have Ste Summers squash on and
Jasmine rice uh we like to kind of
Bounce all over the place with different
Rices to kind of expose them to as many
different flavors as we can to if staff
is not going to eat the same food as the
kids then I definitely see that there's
something wrong with it um we're trying
to make it more palatable for the staff
and more palatable for the kids so
everyone's enjoying the meal and we kind
of encourage us to have to eat with the
kids we want to have the peer to student
ratio you know kind of connecting and
see you know that they're actually
eating the same
thing it's very unlikely that someone
would be able to produce a high quality
meal for 90 cents or
less out of the 180 that are out there
uh we don't use any um I think we tried
to use one I think that was crushed
tomatoes about 4 years ago and they told
us if we wanted those that we had to go
to New Jersey to pick them up and um
it's not worth us for us financially or
in any sense to really drive to another
state to get a can of dice Tomatoes you
need to Source a lot fresher ingredients
a lot fresher items uh more nutritious
items more raw items any child that gets
exposed to
food in a meaningful way whether it's a
classroom Garden or mom or dad spends
time with that child while they're
preparing dinner that child becomes
emotionally vested and food is about
sharing and Community if they feel a
part of the process of preparing the
food seeing where the food comes from
when it hits the table and everybody's
zooing and awing and taking nutrition
and sharing great times and having all
of this going on that's exciting to a
child and they want to take ownership of
that they want to be a part of that and
it happens immediately
bananas granola grola what's that yogurt
yummy
[Music]
t
t yummy
wow this is really good Miss Taurus
wow there was definitely a need I saw
the need um all the children bought to
school were uh unhealthy snacks sugary
snacks totally unhealthy and I Came Upon
the wellness Council project which is a
program from the Department of Education
we're going to look at pictures Kon and
we're going to decide if something is
healthy or if it is
unhealthy the main focus of this program
is to come up with a wellness um policy
for the entire school where the school
decides what what the needs are for the
school what you want to do in your
school and what we wanted to do was to
get rid of junk food so in our wellness
policy we wrote the main thing that we
wanted was to get rid of junky snacks in
the school to have the children bring in
healthy snacks in Pre kindergarten and
kindergarten and that's basically how we
got
[Music]
started in order for for the school to
become healthy all we needed was to have
a committee of teachers that were
interested and parents and we had all of
that we
have carrots and app carrots and apples
organic carrots and organic apples and
we're not even going to eat them we take
the
carrot we put it
in and now comes the
juice
it's not just teaching reading and
writing you know teaching someone how to
eat and how to eat healthy I think
that's a
[Music]
[Applause]
gift your thumb up if you like
it in addition to not selling any junk
food in the
school not even at P ta fundraiser or
any other type of fundraiser that we
have in the school we decided just that
we weren't going to do it because if we
didn't allow the children to bring
in unhealthy snacks we how could we sell
them on the same token um we didn't
allow teachers to eat unhealthy snacks
again teachers are role models and if we
don't want the children to chew gum they
can't chew gum either so it went a those
lines and like that's how you know we
became healthy and like slowly it just
spread throughout the school when you
guys go home your parents are the ones
in charge of feeding right but when you
come to school the school's in charge of
feeding and this was totally by chance I
just received this in my mail box and
it's an article it's a it's a Kids
magazine a Weekly Reader if I subscribe
to it you can always you know get it in
the classroom but it talks about from
Farm to
you currently only about half of schools
serve these healthy foods every day did
you let me read that again currently
means right now so right now only about
half of schools serve these healthy
foods every day with me
[Music]
11 who's
next Kevin Kevin e do you want a math
question or a reading question reading
okay what is one health benefit of a
strawberry um it heals cuts and bruises
very good come take your
smoothie okay thank you next person
um I want I wanted to do it I wanted to
before I retire I wanted to give
something bigger I'm I'm more than you
know than I've done with the children
and the parents in my career and I felt
that this was it like I wanted to you
know share being healthy with them and
exercising and how good you feel I I
just think that's like the most
wonderful thing you can do exercise and
eat healthy and it's not just good for
you it's good for the planet it's good
for
everybody kids the children in the class
will walk in place walk in place walk in
place the children in the class will
walk in place because they're hey
kids you know I didn't get
killed you know like the kids love it
and just I don't know just the fact that
the children are so receptive to it and
they're always showing me what's healthy
what's not healthy you know it's like oh
my God that they want to know the thing
for me with children is they're so
vulnerable so so they'll do what you
want them to do if you tell them right
and if you talk sweetly to them and they
don't really have a say nobody really
listens to them they don't you know come
to school from Mars they come to school
from their neighborhoods they come to
school from the environment so there's a
much larger discussion that needs to
take place of which we're a part there's
a sort of mood out there that food does
matter and again within our environment
as restricted as it is sometimes there's
a real desire to change but there are
boundaries and the question is how does
one push those boundaries the whole
country looks to New York City to see
what they do the whole country says if
New York City can do it we can do
it New York City we have an additional
Challenge and that challenge is really
size we do about you know depending on
the the day in the neighborhood of about
860,000 meals a day uh that includes
breakfast lunch a little bit of supper
but primarily breakfast and and lunch
with lunch being the biggest component
of our
program I think that school food in in
NYC is just such a great Forerunner for
the rest of the country small towns and
big cities alike um they restructured
everything and they made the choice as a
community as a school community that
they were going to prioritize this to
get the kids healthier to get them to
pay more attention in class to get
better grades and to just get better
attendance out of them they realized
that this was a big component and we've
started this about 5 six years ago with
little things but perhaps not so little
changing the name of our organization
from the office of school food nutrition
services to school food that's what
we're about we changed the uniforms of
our staff from an Institutional white
uniform that had the feel of a hospital
or a prison uh which gives a certain
mentality in an aura we changed that to
a little fancy for us we have a um a
sort of crimson top and khaki bottoms
just just to make people feel that we
are we have a brand we're investing in
our brand and a brand means something we
have so many schools contacting us and
asking for our help that we can't keep
up with it um everything is in place we
know what to do and the schools want to
do it and it's really it's just a matter
of of having the resources to really
reach all the people that we want to
reach and it's been so encouraging to
see how kids really do take it on and
they love it it's an empowering thing to
be able to cook and share great meals
with their family and it really makes
them so much their better students they
told me that their IQs are better that
their attendance is better and I've had
students just have total turnarounds
based on changing in their diet it
became a somewhat logical move for us to
move into the school system because we
were basically feeding the families the
teachers and a lot of the young people
already and people were starting to ask
us well how can I get my my children to
eat better in fact through the years I
think I I could count 15 to 20 times
parents parents have come up to us and
said how can I get this food into my
school for my child my kid goes to
school he or she's eating awfully and
then Belle kind of went off for joying
myself well let's look into that let's
see if we can help start with as I would
say one child now it's up to thousands
it's quite incredible to see it
[Music]
happening
we are unconscious about what we're
eating and what we're feeding our
[Music]
children and I believe that we could
make big changes in our health by
changing the food in our schools and in
our
homes I feel like I've struggled with
this for a long time I watch our kids I
continue to watch what they're eating I
continue to hear them be angry about
what they're eating um and I know they
don't know enough and I don't know
enough so I don't know how to help them
transition I don't know um just how to
make some changes that will be sign ific
for them and impactful for them so I'm
excited to have a chance to talk to
people who have actually that understand
it that know how to help us do it and
you know the assistant principal that's
joining us that she's done it you know
she's done some things around wellness
and proper nutrition that I think will
really help our kids so I'm excited to
hear from from her what lessons we can
take and and open do in our
school hi you you I'm Joan they're being
turned down in job situations they're
being turned down in the military
they're being turned down by the medical
establishment I mean they're they're
setting themselves for a very very bad
life and lifes
[Music]
span through the healthy school program
we read I read every morning and I do it
I love to read it I read um a little
something about being well being healthy
and the kids then when they see me in
the hall they'll mention it they'll say
oh miss malice you said that to be
healthy we should eat more beans or and
they're so cute they remember whatever
you tell them you know they internalize
so we have kids that are struggling with
their health um for sure and I think we
have unfortunately I think we have as
many faculty probably that are
struggling with issues um of health and
what they're eating and there isn't a
lot of Education um and there isn't a
lot of access and you also have children
to take care of a lot of them here I've
seen a lot of them in the hallways and
they're all these beautiful faces
looking for you for for guidance and
they're counting on you I really want to
I would love to have us have the meeting
with the lunch staff or whomever the
regional director whoever that is I'd
like to do that in the next couple weeks
you got it we'll meet with the regional
director of the Coalition for healthy
school food Amy Hamlin and we'll get you
started okay people are being programmed
to think well I can eat and live anyway
want abuse myself and somebody in a
white coat is going to hook me up and
change the oil and make me okay again
it's a tough one it's really been
program worse than ever we're up to like
a third generation of that kind of
thinking and it's hard to overcome and
it's not only with the children it's
with the adults too see they they they
kind of accept a lower level of
performance and health and well-being we
we got to get them to connect with the
idea that what they're eating is really
affecting their life in the present and
looking
forward we are the leaders of the world
that's not a god-given right that's
something that we've earned over time
and if we want to continue to be the
model for the world uh then the folks
that are going to be doing that are
sitting at our tables right now uh and
whether you have one at your own table
or not you ought to be concerned about
that the media environment in this
country is also backwards where all the
news programs will rush to cover one
child who is missing or has been
abducted because we can get angry at
some mysterious one person who took a
child but when we then turn the cameras
onto our population of obese and sick
children that means we're pointing the
cameras back at
ourselves we're actually looking at
ourselves and how we're treating the
rest of the kids and that problem is too
embarrassing for most people to look at
it's easier to care about one child we
can really do nothing about than all the
children who are around us every day
with a problem we don't know how to
solve we basically know that the diet
industry fails every everyone and so
what do you
do the global economy is shaky at best
natural disasters layer on layer of them
it's a dark time don't you want some
good news don't you want something that
you can literally close your eyes and
imagine actually achieving in a
generation this is it this is that thing
this is that thing everybody can agree
upon it's about our kids it's about the
health of this country it's the thing
everybody can come together and actually
do there is no reason I can imagine that
people wouldn't be in favor of making
sure kids are
healthy if you're involved in your
school you know what they're serving in
the cafeteria and you will demand that
it be better you have to be involved you
can't just leave it to someone else to
care more about your child than you care
but I definitely believe it can be done
and and we're proof that it can be done
because we're doing it it it's
really well you get hungry for more once
you start and everybody can do something
everybody I would make um like spaghetti
with tomato sauce and like lots of
healthy stuff inside of it I will make
apples that are healthy and they don't
have no scratches on them I put
strawberries and and mango and
watermelon and ch
and and I would give them like all kinds
of
[Music]
vegetables